<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://teodorov.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://teodorov.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2024-10-10T12:30:26+00:00</updated><id>https://teodorov.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>Cip&apos;s homepage </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Multiverse Debugging</title><link href="https://teodorov.github.io/blog/2024/multiverse_debugging/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Multiverse Debugging"/><published>2024-10-10T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-10-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://teodorov.github.io/blog/2024/multiverse_debugging</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://teodorov.github.io/blog/2024/multiverse_debugging/"><![CDATA[<p><strong>Multiverse debugging</strong> offers a powerful toolset for addressing the inherent complexity and non-determinism in concurrent systems. It opens new possibilities for developers and researchers to understand, analyze, optimize, and improve system reliability and performance.</p> <p>The concept of the <em>multiverse</em>, though controversial in philosophy <a href="#1">[1]</a> and physics <a href="#2">[2]</a>, has gained traction in psychology <a href="#3">[3]</a> and neurology <a href="#4">[4]</a>, where multiverse analysis addresses the researcher’s degrees of freedom issue <a href="#5">[5]</a>. In mathematics, the multiverse framework is seen in foundational interpretations of set theory <a href="#6">[6]</a>. In engineering, Leslie Lamport’s Temporal Logic of Actions (TLA) <a href="#7">[7]</a> conceptualizes system specifications within an implicit underlying universe. This framework complements Edward Lee’s view on engineering models <a href="#8">[8]</a>, where engineers are seen as creators of their design universes.</p> <p>In computer science, the multiverse concept was first introduced in <a href="#10">[10]</a> to address challenges in debugging concurrent actor programs. <strong>Multiverse debugging</strong> proposes to explore all potential program behaviors, paralleling modal temporal logics and Kripke’s possible worlds interpretations <a href="#9">[9]</a>. The idea of <strong>multiverse debugging</strong> was extended to the formal analysis of behavioral specifications <a href="#11">[11]</a><a href="#12">[12]</a><a href="#13">[13]</a>, where it served as a cohesive metaphor for integrating debugging and model-checking <a href="#11">[11]</a>. This integration enhances breakpoint expressivity <a href="#11">[11]</a> and facilitates interactive analysis of complex systems <a href="#13">[13]</a>. Early scalability concerns <a href="#10">[10]</a> were mitigated by M. Pasquier et al. in <a href="#12">[12]</a>, who demonstrated that <strong>multiverse debugging</strong> could be optimized through the integration of a variety of under-approximation techniques <a href="#14">[14]</a>.</p> <h2 id="references">References</h2> <p><a id="1">[1]</a> S. Friederich, Multiverse Theories: A Philosophical Perspective. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2021.</p> <p><a id="2">[2]</a> John F. Donoghue. The multiverse and particle physics. Annual Review of Nuclear and Particle Science, 66(Volume 66, 2016):1–21, 2016.</p> <p><a id="3">[3]</a> Steegen, S., Tuerlinckx, F., Gelman, A., &amp; Vanpaemel, W. (2016). Increasing Transparency Through a Multiverse Analysis. Perspectives on Psychological Science, 11(5), 702-712. https://doi.org/10.1177/1745691616658637</p> <p><a id="4">[4]</a> Clayson, Peter E. (2024-03-01). “Beyond single paradigms, pipelines, and outcomes: Embracing multiverse analyses in psychophysiology”. International Journal of Psychophysiology. 197: 112311. doi:10.1016/j.ijpsycho.2024.112311. ISSN 0167-8760</p> <p><a id="5">[5]</a> Wicherts, Jelte M.; Veldkamp, Coosje L. S.; Augusteijn, Hilde E. M.; Bakker, Marjan; van Aert, Robbie C. M.; van Assen, Marcel A. L. M. (2016). “Degrees of Freedom in Planning, Running, Analyzing, and Reporting Psychological Studies: A Checklist to Avoid p-Hacking”. Frontiers in Psychology. 7: 1832. doi:10.3389/fpsyg.2016.01832. PMC 5122713. PMID 27933012.</p> <p><a id="6">[6]</a> D. Hamkins, “The Set-theoretic Multiverse,” The Review of Symbolic Logic, vol. 5, no. 3, pp. 416–449, 2012. doi:10.1017/S1755020311000359</p> <p><a id="7">[7]</a> Leslie Lamport. 1994. The temporal logic of actions. ACM Trans. Program. Lang. Syst. 16, 3 (May 1994), 872–923. https://doi.org/10.1145/177492.177726</p> <p><a id="8">[8]</a> Edward A. Lee. 2018. Modeling in engineering and science. Commun. ACM 62, 1 (January 2019), 35–36. https://doi.org/10.1145/3231590.</p> <p><a id="9">[9]</a> Raymond D. Bradley, Norman Swartz, Possible Worlds – An Introduction to Logic and its Philosophy, Hackett Publishing (1979).</p> <p><a id="10">[10]</a> Carmen Torres Lopez, Robbert Gurdeep Singh, Stefan Marr, Elisa Gonzalez Boix, and Christophe Scholliers. Multiverse Debugging: Non-Deterministic Debugging for Non-Deterministic Programs (Brave New Idea Paper). In 33rd European Conference on Object-Oriented Programming (ECOOP 2019). Leibniz International Proceedings in Informatics (LIPIcs), Volume 134, pp. 27:1-27:30, Schloss Dagstuhl – Leibniz-Zentrum für Informatik (2019) https://doi.org/10.4230/LIPIcs.ECOOP.2019.27</p> <p><a id="11">[11]</a> Matthias Pasquier, <strong>Ciprian Teodorov</strong>, Frédéric Jouault , Matthias Brun , Luka Le Roux. Temporal Breakpoints for Multiverse Debugging. Software Language Engineering 2023, Oct 2023, Lisbonne, Portugal.</p> <p><a id="12">[12]</a> Matthias Pasquier, <strong>Ciprian Teodorov</strong>, Frédéric Jouault , Matthias Brun , Luka Le Roux. Practical multiverse debugging through user-defined reductions. MODELS ‘22: ACM/IEEE 25th International Conference on Model Driven Engineering Languages and Systems, Oct 2022, Montreal Quebec Canada, Canada. pp.87-97, ⟨10.1145/3550355.3552447⟩.</p> <p><a id="13">[13]</a> Matthias Pasquier, <strong>Ciprian Teodorov</strong>, Frédéric Jouault , Matthias Brun , Loïc Lagadec. Debugging Paxos in the UML Multiverse. MODELS-C/MoDeVVa, Oct 2023, Västerås, Sweden.</p> <p><a id="14">[14]</a> Radek Pelanek. Reduction and Abstraction Techniques for Model Checking. Ph.D. Thesis, Masaryk University, 2006.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="research"/><category term="debugging"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[a brief introduction to multiverse debugging]]></summary></entry></feed>